The first image he told me about was of
three children on a road in Iceland, in 1965.
He said that for him
it was the image of happiness...
and also that he had tried several times
to link it to other images...
but it never worked.
He wrote me...
one day I'll have to put it all alone
at the beginning of a film...
with a long piece of black leader.
If they don't see happiness in the picture,
at least they'll see the black.
He wrote: "I'm just back from Hokkaido,
the Northern Island.
Rich and hurried Japanese take the plane,
others take the ferry:
waiting, immobility,
snatches of sleep.
Curiously all of that makes me think
of a past or future war:
night trains, air raids,
fallout shelters.
Small fragments of war
enshrined in everyday life.
He liked the fragility of those moments
suspended in time.
Those memories whose only function it being
to leave behind nothing but memories.
He wrote...
"I've been round the world several times
and now only banality still interests me".
On this trip I've tracked it
with the relentlessness of a bounty hunter.
At dawn we'll be in Tokyo.
He used to write me from Africa.
He contrasted African time to European time,
and also to Asian time.
He said that in the 19th century
mankind had come to terms with space,
and that the great question of the 20th was
the coexistence of different concepts of time.
By the way, did you know that there are emus
in the Île de France?
He wrote me that in the Bijagós Islands
it's the young girls who choose their fiancées.
He wrote me that in the suburbs of Tokyo
there is a temple consecrated to cats.
I wish I could convey to you the simplicity,
the lack of affectation...
of this couple who had come to place
an inscribed wooden slat in the cat cemetery,
so their cat Tora would be protected.
No she wasn't dead, only run away.
But on the day of her death no one
would know how to pray for her,
how to intercede with death so that
he would call her by her right name.
So they had to come there,
both of them, under the rain,
to perform the rite that would repair
the web of time where it had been broken.
He wrote me...
"I will have spent my life trying to
understand the function of remembering,
"which is not the opposite of forgetting,
but rather its lining.
"We do not remember, we rewrite memory
much as history is rewritten.
How can one remember thirst?
He didn't like to dwell on poverty,
but in everything he wanted to show
there were also the 4-Fs of the Japanese model.
A world full of bums, of lumpens,
of outcasts, of Koreans.
Too broke to afford drugs,
they'd get drunk on beer, on fermented milk.
This morning in Namidabashi, twenty minutes
from the glories of the center city,
a character took his revenge on society
by directing traffic at the crossroads.
Luxury for them would be
one of those large bottles of sake...
that are poured over tombs
on the day of the dead.
I paid for a round in a bar
in Namidabashi.
It's the kind of place that allows people
to stare at each other with equality.
The threshold below which every man is
as good as any other.. and knows it.
He told me about the Jetty on Fogo,
in the Cape Verde islands.
How long have they been there
waiting for the boat...
patient as pebbles,
but ready to jump?
They are a people of wanderers,
of navigators, of world travelers.
They fashioned themselves through
cross-breeding here on these rocks...
that the Portuguese used
as a marshaling yard for their colonies.
A people of nothing, a people of emptiness,
a vertical people.
Frankly, have you ever heard
of anything stupider...
than to say to people as they teach
in film schools, not to look at the camera?
He used to write to me: the Sahel is not only
what is shown of it when it is too late.
It's a land that drought seeps
into like water into a leaking boat.
The animals resurrected for the time of
a carnival in Bissau will be petrified again,
as soon as a new attack
has changed the savannah into a desert.
This is a state of survival that
the rich countries have forgotten.
With one exception...
UN Japan.
My constant comings and goings
are not a search for contrasts.
They are a journey
to the two extreme poles of survival.
He spoke to me of Sei Shonagon,
a lady in waiting to Princess Sadako
at the beginning of the 11th century...
in the Heian period.
Do we ever know where history is really made?
Rulers ruled and used complicated strategies
to fight one another.
Real power was in the hands
of a family of hereditary regents.
The emperor's court had become
nothing more...
than a place of intrigues
and intellectual games.
By learning to draw a sort
of melancholy comfort...
from the contemplation
of the tiniest things...
this small group of idlers left a mark
on Japanese sensibility...
much deeper than the mediocre thundering
of the politicians.
Shonagon had a passion for lists...
the list of 'elegant things'...
'distressing things...
or even of 'things not worth doing'.
One day she got the idea of drawing up a list
of...
'things that quicken the heart'.
Not a bad criterion I realize
when I'm filming.
I bow to the economic miracle...
but what I want to show you
are the neighborhood celebrations.
He wrote me...
"Coming back through the Chiba coast
I thought of Shonagon's list,
of all those signs one has only to name
to quicken the heart, just name.
To us, a sun is not quite a sun
unless it's radiant...
and a spring not quite a spring
unless it is limpid.
Here to place adjectives would be so rude
as leaving price tags on purchases.
Japanese poetry never modifies.
There is a way of saying...
boat, rock, mist, frog, crow, hail, heron,
chrysanthemum...
that includes them all.
Newspapers have been filled recently
with the story of a man from Nagoya.
The woman he loved died last year
and he drowned himself in work...
Japanese style, like a madman.
It seems he even made
an important discovery in electronics.
And then in the month of May he killed himself.
They say he could not stand
hearing the word 'spring'.
He described me his reunion with Tokyo:
like a cat who has come home
from vacation in his basket...
immediately starts
to inspect familiar places.
He ran off to see if everything
was where it should be:
the Ginza owl, the Shimbashi locomotive...
the temple of the fox at the top
of the Mitsukoshi department store...
which he found invaded
by little girls and rock singers.
He was told that it was now little girls
who made and unmade stars...
the producers shuddered before them.
He was told that a disfigured woman
took off her mask in front of passers-by...
and scratched them
if they did not find her beautiful.
Everything interested him.
He who didn't give a damn,
if the Dodgers won the pennant...
or about the results
of the Daily Double...
asked feverishly how Chiyonofuji had done
in the last sumo tournament.
He asked for news of the imperial family,
of the crown prince,...
of the oldest mobster in Tokyo...
who appears regularly on television
to teach goodness to children.
These simple joys he had never felt...
of returning to a country,
a house, a family home.
But twelve million anonymous inhabitants
could supply him with them.
He wrote...
"Tokyo is a city crisscrossed by trains,
tied together with electric wire...
she shows her veins.
They say that television
makes her people illiterate.
As for me, I've never seen
so many people reading in the streets.
Perhaps they read only in the street...
or perhaps they just pretend to read,
these yellow men.
I make my appointments at Kinokuniya,
the big bookshop in Shinjuku.
The graphic genius that allowed
the Japanese to invent CinemaScope...
ten centuries before the movies...
compensates a little for the sad fate
of the comic strip heroines,
victims of heartless story writers
and of castrating censorship.
Sometimes they escape,
and you find them again on the walls.
The entire city is a comic strip.
It's Planet Manga.
How can one fail
to recognize the statuary...
that goes from plasticized baroque
to Stalin central?
And the giant faces with eyes that weigh down
on the comic book readers,
pictures bigger than people,
voyeurizing the voyeurs.
At nightfall the megalopolis
breaks down into villages,
with its country cemeteries
in the shadow of banks...
with its stations and temples.
Each district of Tokyo once again becomes
a tidy ingenuous little town...
nestling amongst the skyscrapers.
The small bar in Shinjuku reminded him
of that Indian flute...
whose sound can only be heard
by whomever is playing it.
He might have cried out if it was
in a Godard film or a Shakespeare play...
"Where should this music be?"
Later he told me he had eaten
at the restaurant in Nishi-nippori...
where Mr. Yamada practices
the difficult art of 'action cooking'.
He said that by watching carefully
Mr. Yamada's gestures...
and his way of mixing
the ingredients...
one could meditate usefully
on certain fundamental concepts...
common to painting,
philosophy, and karate.
He claimed that Mr. Yamada possessed
in his humble way the essence of style,
and consequently that was up to him...
to use his invisible brush to write upon
this first day in Tokyo the words...
'the end'.
I've spent the day in front of my TV set,
that memory box.
I was in Nara with the sacred deers.
I was taking a picture without knowing
that in the 15th century Basho had written:
"The willow sees the heron's image...
upside down".
The commercial becomes
a kind of haiku to the eye,
used to Western atrocities
in this field.
Not understanding obviously
adds to the pleasure.
For one slightly hallucinatory moment
I had the impression that I spoke Japanese,
but it was a cultural program on NHK
about Gérard de Nerval.
8:40, Cambodia.
From Jean Jacques Rousseau
to the Khmer Rouge...
coincidence,
or the sense of history?
In Apocalypse Now, Brando said a few definitive
and incommunicable sentences:
"Horror has a face and a name"...
"You must make a friend of horror"...
To cast out the horror
that has a name and a face...
you must give it another name
and another face.
Japanese horror movies have the cunning beauty
of certain corpses.
Sometimes one is stunned
by so much cruelty.
One seeks its sources in the Asian peoples
long familiarity with suffering...
that requires that even pain
be ornate.
And then comes the reward...
the monsters are laid out,
Natsume Masako arises.
Absolute beauty
also has a name and a face.
But the more you watch Japanese television,
the more you feel it's watching you.
Even television newscast bears
witness to the fact...
that the magical function of the eye
is at the center of all things.
It's election time.
The winning candidates black out
the empty eye of Daruma...
the spirit of luck,
while losing candidates...
sad but dignified,
carry off their one-eyed Daruma.
The images most difficult to figure out
are those of Europe.
I watched the pictures of a film
whose soundtrack will be added later.
It took me six months for Poland.
Meanwhile, I have no difficulty
with local earthquakes.
But I must say that last night's quake
helped me greatly to grasp a problem.
Poetry is born of insecurity:
wandering Jews, quaking Japanese;
by living on a rug that jesting nature
is ever ready to pull out from under them...
they've got into the habit of moving
about in a world of appearances...
fragile, fleeting, revocable,
of trains that fly from planet to planet,
of samurai fighting in an immutable past.
That's called
'the impermanence of things'.
I did it all.
All the way to the evening shows for adults,
so called.
The same hypocrisy as in the comic strips,
but it's a coded hypocrisy.
Censorship is not the mutilation of the show,
it is the show.
The code is the message.
It points to the absolute by hiding it.
That's what religions have always done.
That year...
a new face appeared among the great ones
that blazon the streets of Tokyo: the Pope's.
Treasures that had never left
the Vatican...
were shown on the seventh floor
of the Sogo department store.
He wrote me:
"Curiosity of course, and the glimmer
of industrial espionage in the eye.
"I imagine them bringing out
within two years time...
a more efficient
and less expensive version of Catholicism.
But there's also the fascination
associated with the sacred...
even when it's someone else's.
So when will the third floor of Macy's harbor
an exhibition of Japanese sacred signs...
such as can be seen at Josen-kai
on the island of Hokkaido?
At first one smiles at this place
which combines a museum...
a chapel, and a sex shop.
As always in Japan, one admires the fact that
the walls between the realms are so thin...
that one can in the same breath contemplate
a statue, buy an inflatable doll...
and give the goddess of fertility
the small offering...
that always accompanies her displays.
Displays whose frankness would make the
stratagems of the television incomprehensible,
if it did not at the same time say
that a sex is visible...
only on condition
of being severed from a body.
One would like to believe in a world
before the fall.
Inaccessible to the complications
of a Puritanism...
whose phony shadow has been imposed on it
by American occupation.
Where people who gather
laughing around the votive fountain,
the woman who touches it
with a friendly gesture...
share in the same cosmic innocence.
The second part of the museum...
with its couples of stuffed animals...
would then be the earthly paradise
as we have always dreamed it.
Not so sure...
Animal innocence may be a trick
for getting around censorship.
But perhaps also the mirror
of an impossible reconciliation.
And even without original sin
this earthly paradise may be a paradise lost.
In the glossy splendour
of the gentle animals of Josen-kai...
I read the fundamental rift
of Japanese society...
the rift that separates men from women.
In life it seems to show itself
in two ways only...
violent slaughter, or a discreet melancholy
resembling Sei Shonagon's
which the Japanese express
in a single untranslatable word.
So this bringing down of man
to the level of the beasts...
against which the fathers
of the church invade...
becomes here the challenge of the beasts
to the poignancy of things,
to a melancholy whose color I can give you
by copying a few lines from Samura Koichi:
"Who said that time heals all wounds?
"It would be better to say that time
heals everything except wounds.
"With time, the hurt of separation
loses its real limits.
"With time, the desired body
will soon disappear,
"and if the desiring body has already ceased
to exist for the other,
"then what remains is a wound...
disembodied."
He wrote me
that the Japanese secret...
what Lévi-Strauss had called
'the poignancy of things'...
implied the faculty of communion
with things...
of entering into them,
of being them for a moment.
It was normal that in their turn
they should be like us...
perishable and immortal.
He wrote me:
"Animism is a familiar notion in Africa,
it is less often applied in Japan.
What then shall we call
this diffuse belief...
according to which every fragment
of creation has its invisible counterpart?
When they build a factory
or a skyscraper...
they begin with a ceremony
to appease the god who owns the land.
There is a ceremony for brushes, for abacuses,
and even for rusty needles.
There's one on the 25th of September
for the repose of the soul of broken dolls.
The dolls are piled up in the temple
of Kiyomitsu consecrated to Kannon...
the goddess of compassion...
and are burned in public.
I look to the participants.
I think the people who saw off
the kamikaze pilots...
had the same look on their faces.
He wrote me that the pictures
of Guinea-Bissau...
ought to be accompanied by music
from the Cape Verde islands.
That would be our contribution to the unity
dreamed of by Amilcar Cabral.
Why should so small a countryand one so poor
interest the world?
They did what they could,
they freed themselves.
They chased out the Portuguese.
They traumatized the Portuguese army
to such an extent...
that it gave rise to a movement
that overthrew the dictatorship,
and led one for a moment to believe
in a new revolution in Europe.
Who remembers all that?
History throws its empty bottles
out the window.
This morning I was on the dock at Pidjiguity,
where everything began in 1959...
when the first victims of the struggle
were killed.
It may be as difficult to recognize Africa
in this leaden fog...
as it is to recognize struggle in the rather
dull activity of tropical longshoremen.
Rumor has it that
every third world leader...
coined the same phrase
the morning after independence:
"Now the real problems start".
Cabral never got a chance to say it.
He was assassinated first.
But the problems started, and went on,
and are still going on.
Rather unexciting problems
for revolutionary romanticism:
To work, to produce,
to distribute...
to overcome postwar exhaustion,
temptations of power and privilege.
Ah well...
after all, history only tastes bitter to those
who expected it to be sugar coated.
My personal problem is more specific:
how to film the ladies of Bissau?
Apparently, the magical function of the eye
was working against me there.
It was in the marketplaces
of Bissau and Cape Verde...
that I could stare at them
again with equality.
I see her.
She saw me.
She knows that I see her.
She drops me her glance...
but just at an angle where it is still possible
to act as though it was not addressed to me.
And at the end the real glance,
straightforward...
that lasted a twenty-fourth of a second,
the length of a film frame.
All women have a built-in grain
of indestructibility.
And men's task has always been to make them
realize it as late as possible.
African men are just as good
at this task as others.
But after a close look at African women,
I wouldn't necessarily bet on the men.
He told me the story of the dog Hachiko.
A dog waited every day
for his master at the station.
The master died,
and the dog didn't know it...
and he continued to wait all his life.
People were moved
and brought him food.
After his death a statue
was erected in his honor...
in front of which sushi and rice cakes
are still placed
so that the faithful soul of Hachiko
will never go hungry.
Tokyo is full of these tiny legends,
and of mediating animals.
The Mitsukoshi lion stands guard
on the frontiers...
of what was once the empire
of Mr. Okada...
a great collector of French paintings,
the man who hired
the Château of Versailles...
to celebrate the hundredth anniversary
of his department stores.
In the computer section I've seen young
Japanese exercising their brain muscles...
like the young Athenians at the Palaistra.
They have a war to win.
The history books of the future will perhaps
place the battle of integrated circuits...
at the same level
as Salamis and Agincourt,
but willing to honor the unfortunate adversary
by leaving other fields to him.
Men's fashions this season are placed
under the sign of John Kennedy.
Like an old votive turtle
stationed in the corner of a field...
every day he saw Mr. Akao...
the president
of the Japanese Patriotic Party...
trumpeting from the heights
of his rolling balcony...
against the international communist plot.
He wrote me:
"The automobiles of the extreme right
with their flags and megaphones...
are part of Tokyo's landscape.
Mr. Akao is their focal point.
I think he'll have his statue
like the dog Hachiko,
at this crossroads from which he departs
only to go and prophesy on the battlefields.
He was at Narita in the sixties.
Peasants fighting against the building
of an airport on their land,
and Mr. Akao denouncing the hand of Moscow
behind everything that moved.
Yurakucho is the political space of Tokyo.
Once upon a time I saw bonzes
pray for peace in Vietnam there.
Today young right-wing activists...
protest against the annexation
of the Northern Islands by the Russians.
Sometimes they are answered
that the commercial relations of Japan...
with the abominable occupier
of the North...
are a thousand times better...
than with the American ally who is always
whining about economic aggression.
Ah, nothing is simple.
On the other sidewalk,
the Left has the floor.
The Korean Catholic opposition leader,
Kim Dae Jung...
kidnapped in Tokyo in '73
by the South Korean gestapo...
is threatened with the death sentence.
A group has begun a hunger strike.
Some very young militants are trying
to gather signatures in his support.
I went back to Narita for the birthday
of one of the victims of the struggle.
The demo was unreal.
I had the impression of acting in Brigadoon,
of waking up ten years later
in the midst of the same players...
with the same blue lobsters of police,
the same helmeted adolescents,
the same banners and the same slogan:
"Down with the airport".
Only one thing has been added:
the airport precisely.
But with its single runway
and the barbed wire that chokes it...
it looks more besieged
than victorious.
My pal Hayao Yamaneko has found a solution:
if the images of the present don't change,
then change the images of the past.
He showed me the clashes of the sixties
treated by his synthesizer:
pictures that are less deceptive he says
with the conviction of a fanatic...
than those you see on television.
At least they proclaim themselves
to be what they are:
images...
not the portable and compact form
of an already inaccessible reality.
Hayao calls his machine's world the 'zone',
an homage to Tarkovsky.
What Narita brought back to me,
like a shattered hologram,
was an intact fragment
of the generation of the sixties.
If to love without illusions is still to love,
I can say that I loved it.
It was a generation that often exasperated me,
for I didn't share its utopia of uniting
in a common struggle...
those who revolt against poverty
and those who revolt against wealth.
But it screamed out that gut reaction that
better adjusted voices no longer knew how...
or no longer dared to utter.
I met peasants there who had come
to know themselves through the struggle.
Concretely it had failed.
At the same time, all they had won
in their understanding of the world...
could have been won
only through the struggle.
As for the students...
some massacred each other in the mountains
in the name of revolutionary purity,
while others had studied capitalism
so thoroughly to fight it...
that they now provide it
with its best executives.
Like everywhere else the movement
had its postures and its careerists...
including, and there are some,
those who made a career of martyrdom.
But it carried with it all those who said,
like Ché Guevara, that...
they "trembled with indignation every time
an injustice is committed in the world".
They wanted to give a political meaning
to their generosity...
and their generosity
has outlasted their politics.
That's why I will never allow it to be said
that youth is wasted on the young.
The youth who get together
every weekend at Shinjuku...
obviously know that they are not
on a launching pad toward real life;
but they are life, to be eaten
on the spot like fresh doughnuts.
It's a very simple secret.
The old try to hide it,
and not all the young know it.
The ten-year-old girl who threw her friend...
from the thirteenth floor of a building
after having tied her hands,
because she'd spoken badly of their
class team, hadn't discovered it yet.
Parents who demand an increase
in the number of special telephone lines...
devoted to the prevention
of children's suicides...
find out a little late
that they have kept it all too well.
Rock is an international language
for spreading the secret.
Another is peculiar to Tokyo.
For the takenoko,
twenty is the age of retirement.
They are baby Martians.
I go to see them dance
every Sunday in the park at Yoyogi.
They want people to look at them,
but they don't seem to notice that people do.
They live in a parallel time sphere...
a kind of invisible aquarium wall
separates them from the crowd they attract,
and I can spend a whole afternoon contemplating
the little takenoko girl who is learning
no doubt for the first time,
the customs of her planet.
Beyond that, they wear dog tags,
they obey a whistle, the Mafia rackets them,
and with the exception
of a single group made up of girls...
it's always a boy who commands.
One day he writes to me:
description of a dream.
More and more my dreams find their settings
in the department stores of Tokyo,
the subterranean tunnels that extend them
and run parallel to the city.
A face appears, disappears...
a trace is found, is lost.
All the folklore of dreams
is so much in its place...
that the next day
when I am awake...
I realize that I continue to seek
in the basement labyrinth...
the presence
concealed the night before.
I begin to wonder if those dreams
are really mine...
or if they are part of a totality...
of a gigantic collective dream of which
the entire city may be the projection.
It might suffice to pick up
any one of the telephones...
that are lying around to hear
a familiar voice, or the beating of a heart,
Sei Shonagon's for example.
All the galleries lead to stations...
the same companies own the stores
and the railroads that bear their name.
Keio, Odakyu...
all those names of ports.
The train inhabited by sleeping people
puts together all the fragments of dreams...
makes a single film of them,
the ultimate film.
The tickets from the automatic dispenser
grant admission to the show.